Register of the Shirley Mae Stark papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Shirley Mae Stark papers
1963-1981
1967-1974
91032
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (11.1 linear feet)
The papers of Shirley Mae Stark, wife of American prisoner of war William Stark and advocate on behalf of the American prisoners of war (POWs) in Vietnam, consist of correspondence, newsletters, press releases, bulletins, clippings, other printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating to American POWs during the Vietnam War and their families. The papers include correspondence with and issuances of the Department of the Navy, other United States government officials, and voluntary organizations concerned with the welfare of prisoners of war, especially the National League of Families of American Prisoners in Southeast Asia. Also included are numerous letters from members of the public.
Stark, Shirley Mae.
Access
Collection is open for research. Box 14, folder 3 may not be used without permission of the Archivist.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1930 February 28 Shirley Mae Stark (née Gust) born in Michigan City, Indiana
1930 May 28 William Robert Stark born to George and Gladys Stark in Michigan City, Indiana
1949 October 22 Shirley and William Stark married in Key West, Florida
1951 October 29 Daughter Susan born
1967 May 19 William Stark shot down and captured just south of Hanoi in Vietnam
circa 1967-1973 Shirley Stark worked part-time as a teller at Bank of America and volunteered with POW/MIA advocacy groups.
1973 March 4 William Stark released during Operation Homecoming
Scope and Content of Collection
The Shirley Mae Stark papers, the bulk of which date from 1967 to 1974, document the experience of American POWs and their families during the Vietnam War through correspondence, newsletters, press releases, clippings, other printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia.
After her husband was captured in Vietnam, Shirley Stark became involved with various advocacy groups, particularly the National League of Families of American Prisoners in Southeast Asia, that worked to raise awareness of the plight of missing and captured American soldiers. As a member of these groups, she received correspondence and newsletters providing information about efforts on behalf of POWs/MIAs, which can be found in the Correspondence series, under POW/MIA advocacy groups. She also participated in fundraising activities, which included the sale of rubber stamps, bumper stickers, and bracelets. Examples of some of these items can be found in the Memorabilia series.
Of particular note are the bracelets, each of which featured the name and date of capture of a POW. Individuals who purchased the bracelets could opt to receive further information about the POW and his family, and many went on to correspond with family members and the returned POWs. William Stark’s name was on one of the bracelets, and as a result, there is a large amount of correspondence from members of the public, particularly after his release, inquiring about his well-being and welcoming him home. This can be found in the Correspondence series, under General, particularly in the folders for 1973.
Shirley Stark also received regular updates from the Department of the Navy relating to her husband’s pay and benefits, instructions for sending mail and packages to Vietnam, and the POW situation generally. These letters, many of which included informational attachments, can be found in the Correspondence series, under Department of the Navy. Other Navy and POW-related publications can be found in the Printed Matter series, which also contains clippings collected by Shirley Stark about the experiences of the POWs and their families, the work of the government and advocacy groups, and the return of the POWs to the United States. Some of these articles are specifically about the Stark family. Additional clippings, as well as some correspondence, photographs, and printed matter, can be found in the albums created by Shirley and Gladys Stark in the Oversize Materials series.
National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia.; Navy wives.; Prisoners of war.; United States--Armed Forces.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Prisoners and prisons, North Vietnamese.
- Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 1-13)
  - General, 1967-1974 (Box 1-7)
    Scope and Contents note
    The majority of this series consists of letters received (and in some cases sent) by Shirley Mae Stark and her husband, William Stark. Some letters received by their daughter Susan are included as well. There is also a file of letters received by Mrs. Gladys Stark, William Stark's mother.
    - Undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 1: 5-6)
      Includes correspondence relating to the activities of the National League of Families of American Prisoners in Southeast Asia, mostly in the form of letters requesting bumper stickers or rubber stamps.
    - 1971 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 1: 8, Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    - 1973
      Making up the bulk of this series, the correspondence from 1973 consists of a large number of cards and letters reacting to news of William Stark's release from the POW prison in Vietnam and welcoming him home. Much of this correspondence came from school children, particularly those who had worn the POW bracelet with his name on it.
      - Undated (Box-folder 2: 3-5)
        Correspondence received in 1973 (as evidenced by references to William Stark's return from Vietnam) that is undated.
      - January (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
      - February (Box-folder 3: 3-4)
      - March (Box-folder 3: 5-6, Box-folder 4: 1-4)
      - April (Box-folder 4: 5, Box-folder 5: 1)
      - May (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
      - June (Box-folder 5: 4)
      - July-December (Box-folder 5: 5)
      - Invitations (Box-folder 6: 1-3)
        File created by Shirley Stark consisting of invitations sent to William Stark after his release from Vietnam. Other invitations that were not contained in this file may be found within the rest of the folders of the 1973 subseries.
    - 1974 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Mrs. Gladys Stark, 1967-1973, undated
      Correspondence received (and in some instances sent) by Mrs. Gladys Stark, mother of William Stark.
      - Undated, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 6: 5)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Letters sent to William Stark in Vietnam, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      Handwritten and typed drafts of letters by Shirley and Susan Stark to William Stark while he was a POW in Vietnam. Includes some correspondence from the Department of the Navy, Naval Intelligence Command with suggested revisions to a few of the letters.
    - Letters sent by William Stark from Vietnam, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 7: 2)
      The majority of the letters are photostats or transcriptions handwritten by Shirley Stark.
    - William Stark's response to well-wishers, 1973 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      Form letter sent by William Stark after his return from Vietnam to friends, family, and other well-wishers (particularly those who had worn the POW bracelet with his name on it) expressing gratitude for their support and providing an update on himself and his family.
    - Addressed to others, 1970 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      Consists of correspondence, presumably forwarded to Shirley Stark, addressed to others (there are similar items intermingled with the rest of the general correspondence, though those usually included a note or envelope addressed to Shirley Stark). Of note are letters from the United Nations, the Swedish Embassy, the Swedish Royal Ministry for Foreign Affairs, and the Polish Minister of Foreign Affairs addressed to a Mr. and Mrs. Fitz in response to their letters regarding William Stark and other POWs in Vietnam.
  - Department of the Navy, 1967-1973 (Box 7-9)
    - Bureau of Naval Personnel, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 7: 5-8, Box-folder 8: 1-6)
    - CACO (Casualty Assistance Calls Officer), 1969-1973 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Naval Air Station Miramar, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - Naval Air Station North Island, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 9: 3)
      Includes correspondence from Commander Fleet Air, San Diego and Commander Naval Air Force, U.S. Pacific Fleet.
    - Naval Intelligence Command, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Office of the Chief of Naval Operations, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Other, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 9: 6)
      Correspondence from other branches of the Department of the Navy in San Diego, CA, including: Commandant, Eleventh Naval District; Naval Development and Training Center; Naval Hospital; and the Navy Medical Neuropsychiatric Research Unit (Center for POW Studies).
  - POW/MIA advocacy groups, 1967-1974 (Box 9-12)
    - Committee of Liaison with Families of Servicement Detained in North Vietnam, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 9: 7, Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Concern for Prisoners of War, Inc., 1970-1972 (Box-folder 10: 2-5)
    - League of Wives of American Vietnam Prisoners of War, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 10: 7, Box-folder 11: 1-5, Box-folder 12: 1-2)
    - United We Stand, 1970 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - VIVA (Voices in Vital America), 1971-1973 (Box-folder 12: 4-5)
    - Other, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 12: 6-7)
      Correspondence sent to Shirley Stark from a variety of other POW/MIA and peace advocacy groups, including the Allied War Prisoners Rescue Mission, American Friends Service Committee, Inc., Rescue Line, and POW/MIA Families for Immediate Release, among others.
    - Petitions and sample letters, undated (Box-folder 12: 8)
      Includes blank petitions produced by various advocacy groups addressed generally to heads of state and governments of the world (and specifically to the President of Vietnam and Xuan Thuy of the North Vietnamese Delegation to the Paris Peace Talks) appealing for adherence to the Geneva Conventions in relation to the treatment and release of POWs. Also included are addresses of foreign dignitaries and press for letter-writing campaigns, as well as sample letters.
  - United States government, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
    Includes correspondence sent to Shirley, Susan, and William Stark from The White House, the Department of State, the Secretary of Defense, the Senate, the House of Representatives, and the Veterans Administration. Also includes instructions and forms for applying for insurance benefits under the Social Security Act and for compensation for those who were POWs in Vietnam.
  - Notes and drafts, circa 1967-1973 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    Shirley Stark's (mostly) handwritten notes and drafts of outgoing correspondence. Includes drafts of letters to her husband in Vietnam, as well as to politicians and military personnel regarding the POW situation in Vietnam.
- Subject File, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - Iran hostage bracelet project
    Includes a copy of a letter from Ken Taylor, who was the Canadian ambassador to Iran during the Iran hostage crisis, to Barbara Wyatt, publisher of We Came Home (a book honoring Vietnam POWs), thanking her for sending a copy of the book and referencing a hostage bracelet he received. An excerpt from We Came Home is included. There are also two informational sheets about the Voices for Freedom hostage bracelet project, an order form (which references the Vietnam POW/MIA bracelets), and photocopies of newspaper articles about the hostage crisis and the bracelet project.
- Photographs, undated (Box 13, 21)
  - William Stark (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Family and friends (Box-folder 13: 7, Box-folder 21: 1)
  - Navy and POW-advocacy (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Negatives and slides (Box-folder 13: 9)
- Oversize Material, 1967-1972 (Box 20-21)
  - Scrapbooks, 1967-1972
    Consists of five scrapbooks, organized chronologically, one of which appears to have been created by Gladys Stark (mother of William Stark). Mainly filled with newspaper clippings, the scrapbooks also contain some correspondence, invitations, photographs, programs, and newsletters. Loose material from the front and back of each scrapbook was placed into an envelope and kept with the relevant scrapbook.
- Memorabilia, circa 1970s (Box 14, 21)
  - Awards, 1970, 1974
    - Coronado Floral Association, 1970 April (Box-folder 14: 1)
      Certificate and second prize ribbon from the Coronado Flower Show awarded to 465 "C" Ave (Shirley Stark's address) for home front.
    - Freedoms Foundation at Valley Forge, 1974 February (Box-folder 21: 2)
      Mounted honor certificate given to William Stark in the category of Singing American POWs, 1973, "an outstanding achievement in bringing about a better understanding of the American way of life."
  - Name tags and patch, circa 1973 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    Includes Navy visitor badges for Shirley, Susan, and Gladys Stark; name tags for Shirley and William Stark for the Vietnam Veterans Homecoming Celebration; and an Operation Homecoming Flight to Freedom patch.
  - Name tags, circa 1973 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    Access
    May not be used without permission of the Archivist. Use copies of the items are available in box 14, folder 2.
  - POW advocacy, undated
    Consists of items produced by POW advocacy groups and sold to raise awareness about the POW situation in Vietnam.
    - Bracelets, undated (Box-folder 14: 4)
      The bracelets are engraved with the names of POW/MIA American soldiers (including Commander Stark) and the date they were captured or went missing. Many of the individuals who bought and wore these bracelets corresponded with the families of the soldiers and eventually returned the bracelets to the soldier when he was released.
    - Bumper stickers, undated (Box-folder 14: 5-6)
      Also includes bumper stickers in support of President Nixon.
    - Pin-back buttons, undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - Stickers and rubber stamps, undated (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - Returned parcels packaging, 1967, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 14: 9)
    Outer packaging and tags for care packages sent by Shirley Stark to William Stark while he was in captivity that were refused by the Vietnam Postal Service.
- Printed Matter, 1963-1974 (Box 15-19)
  Some of these items were originally attachments to letters (many sent by the Department of the Navy) that had been separated from the original letters and thus placed with other printed matter.
  - Air Force and Space Digest, "The Forgotten Americans of the Vietnam War: A Special Report on POWs,", 1969 October (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - All Hands, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    Two issues of this publication of the Bureau of Naval Personnel: October 1972 and June 1973.
  - The Amphibian, 1970 (Box-folder 15: 3)
    Bi-weekly publication mailed to all ships and units of the Pacific Fleet Amphibious Force by the Force Public Affairs Office. Includes two issues: October 2, 1970 and December 11, 1970.
  - Bridge & Bay: The Coronado Magazine, Summer 1973 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - Bureau of Social Science Research, Inc., 1963 (Box-folder 15: 5)
    Includes two papers: "Necessary, Permissible, and Obligatory Discourse with Captor Personnel," by Albert D. Biderman, August 1963; and "Roles--Not Rules--For the POW," by Dr. Edgar H. Schein, September 1963.
  - Commanders Digest, 1970 (Box-folder 15: 6)
    Published by the Department of Defense. Includes Vol. 8, No. 8, May 23, 1970; Vol. 8, No. 11, June 13, 1970; and Vol. 8, No. 15, July 11, 1970.
  - Congressional bills and resolutions, 1969 (Box-folder 15: 7)
    Includes the following bills and resolution related to the Vietnam conflict, specifically pertaining to POWs: H.R. 9485, March 25, 1969; H.R. 9486, March 25, 1969; H.R. 9487, March 25, 1969; and H. Con. Res. 360, September 17, 1969.
  - Congressional committee prints, 1970, 1972 (Box-folder 15: 8)
    Includes the following:
    Annual Report for the Year 1969, House Committee on Internal Security, 91st Congress, 1970.
    The Geneva Convention Relative to the Treatment of Prisoners of War With Reservations, if Any, by Governments Participating in Hostilities in Vietnam, Cambodia and Laos, House Committee on Foreign Affairs, Subcommittee on National Security Policy and Scientific Developments, 91st Congress, 1970.
    The Human Cost of Communism in Vietnam, Senate Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws, 92nd Congress, 1972.
    Communist Treatment of Prisoners of War: A Historical Survey, Senate Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws, 92nd Congress, 1972.
  - Congressional hearings, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 15: 9-10)
    Hearing on Problems of Prisoners of War and Their Families Before the Committee on Armed Services, 91st Congress, March 6, 1970.
    American Prisoners of War in Southeast Asia, 1970, Hearings Before the Subcommittee on National Security Policy and Scientific Developments of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, 91st Congress, April 29, May 1, 6, 1970.
    American Prisoners of War in Southeast Asia, 1971, Hearings Before the Subcommittee on National Security Policy and Scientific Developments of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, 92nd Congress, March 23, 24, 25, 30, 31, April 1, 6, 20, 1971.
    American Prisoners of War in Southeast Asia, 1971, Hearings Before the Subcommittee on National Security Policy and Scientific Developments of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, Part Two, 92nd Congress, June 29, August 3, September 28, 1971.
    The Human Cost of Communism in Vietnam, II: The Myth of No Bloodbath, Hearing Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary, 93rd Congress, January 5, 1973.
  - Congressional Record, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 16: 1)
    Includes Vol. 115, No. 149; Vol. 116, No. 18; an excerpt from February 18, 1970; Vol. 116, No. 183; and Vol. 117, No. 33.
  - Current Foreign Policy, "The United States and the People's Republic of China,", 1971 August (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Department of Defense, 1964, 1969, 1972, 1973 (Box-folder 16: 3)
    Includes two pamphlets and two booklets: Code of the U.S. Fighting Man, 1964; Revised Uniformed Services Health Benefits Program, 1969; Information Pamphlet for Families of United States Servicemen Who Are Prisoners of War or Are Missing in Action in Southeast Asia, 1972; and Employment Assistance for Repatriated POW Personnel, January 1973.
  - Department of the Navy, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 16: 4)
    Includes three booklets: Missing in Action and Prisoners of War Family Information, 1969; Missing in Action and Prisoners of War Family Information, 1970; and Egress Recap: Comeleven Plan for the Repatriation of Prisoners of War and Other Detained Navy Personnel from Southeast Asia, 1972. Also included are a printout of recovered prisoners of war, 1973, and a list titled "Fitness Report Information," circa 1973, which were originally tucked inside the Egress Recap booklet.
  - Fighting Man's Bible, Life Publications, 1967 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - The Forge, 1974 April (Box-folder 16: 6)
    Published by the Freedoms Foundation at Valley Forge, San Diego County Women's Chapter.
  - In Brief for the P.O.W., a Catch-up on News from Missing Years, 1973 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - Ladycom, 1970 March (Box-folder 16: 8)
    "The magazine serving military and diplomatic ladies around the world."
  - Life, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 16: 9)
    Includes excerpts from two issues:
    "These Men Had Dropped from Sight," February 12, 1971.
    "When Johnny Comes Marching Home Again - or Doesn't," "It's Like Planning to Get Married Again," and "No Bells for Peace," November 10, 1972.
  - The Link, 1973 July (Box-folder 16: 10)
    A magazine for armed forces personnel.
  - My God, How Can It Be?, Holmes, Joseph R., 1967 (Box-folder 16: 11)
  - Navy Wifeline, Spring 1970 (Box-folder 16: 12)
  - North Islander, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 16: 13)
    Includes two issues: Vol. XXX, No. 26, July 6, 1973; and Vol. XXXI, No. 10, January 25, 1974.
  - The Prisoner of War Problem, 1970 December 28 (Box-folder 16: 14)
    Special analysis published by the American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research.
  - "Questions About the POWs...Before We Make Them Heroes," an Indochina Peace Campaign Report, circa 1973 (Box-folder 16: 15)
  - Trident, 1973 April (Box-folder 16: 16)
    The professional magazine of the Brigade of Midshipmen.
  - U.S. News & World Report, 1973 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    "Was Vietnam Worth It?," April 2, 1973.
    "How the POW's Fought Back," John S. McCain III, May 14, 1973.
  - Veterans Administration, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 17: 2)
    Informational booklets provided by the VA to Commander Stark upon his return from Vietnam. Titles include:
    National Service Life Insurance: Information and Premium Rates for RH Policies for Service-Disabled Veterans, September 1969.
    Servicemen's Group Life Insurance Certificate, September 1970.
    Pointers for the Veteran Homeowner, May 1971.
    Questions & Answers on Guaranteed and Direct Loans for Veterans, May 1971.
    To the Home-Buying Veteran, July 1972.
    Federal Benefits for Veterans and Dependents, January 1973.
  - Viet-Nam Information Notes, 1970 April (Box-folder 17: 3)
  - The Voice of POWs and MIAs, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 17: 4)
    Published by VIVA (Voices in Vital America). Includes five issues: Vol. I, No. 2, October 1972; Vol. I, No. 3, November 1972; Vol. II, No. 1, January/February 1973; Vol. II, No. 3, April 1973; and Vol. II, No. 6, August/September 1973.
  - Miscellany, 1967-1973, undated (Box-folder 17: 5)
    Blank postcards depicting the Washington [D.C.] Hilton and the ROA's Minute Man Memorial, undated.
    Flyer in support of Bob Wilson's campaign for Congress, undated.
    "Send a Letter to North Vietnam," Red Cross PSA, undated.
    Reproduction of a political cartoon by Jeff MacNelly for The Richmond News Leader featuring a North Vietnamese man on a tricycle with a sweater that reads "Jane Fondle for President," undated.
    "My Turn: Col. Robinson Risner. A POW Replies," undated.
    "P.O.W.S. And Now a Darker Story," undated.
    "SVNLNF's Policy Towards the Officers and Men in the U.S. and Alien Army," The South Vietnam National Front for Liberation, undated.
    "Our Policy Toward U.S. and Satellite Prisioners [sic] of War in South Vietnam," The High Command of the South Vietnam Liberation Armed Forces, undated.
    "A Prayer for Prisoners," Kelly, James W., Rear Admiral, CHC, USN, Chief of Chaplains, undated.
    "A Litany for Peace," undated.
    "A Litany for Our POWs and MIAs," undated.
    "World Famous Fighting Falcons Social Roster," October 2, 1967.
    "Social Revolution for the Military," Schweitz, Bob, March 20, 1968.
    "North Vietnam Camp Regulations," February 15, 1969.
    "Mrs. O'Grady Is a Widow," Look Magazine, May 5, 1970.